Guide to the Lathrop Family Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Lathrop family papers
1807-1955
SC0536
Lathrop family.
0.5 Linear feet
These papers pertain to the Lathrop family, in particular Dyer Lathrop and Daniel Shields. Dyer Lathrop's papers, 1820-1849, pertain largely to his business affairs and include letters, bills, notes, and receipts, including accounts with the Spring Street Mission House, 1828-1833. Daniel Shields' papers,1807-1835, largely concern his pension as a Revolutionary soldier and his appointment as Sergeant at Arms for the New York Assembly; other items include a ledger and an appraisal of his estate. Other papers of note in the collection include a list of donations to the Albany Orphan Asylum, 1833; insurance accounts of Charles Lathrop, 1908-1915; and a letter to Elizabeth Shields, Sept. 23, 1850, that mentions the wedding of Jane Lathrop and Leland Stanford.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Jane Lathrop Stanford, wife of Leland Stanford and co-founder of Stanford University, was the daughter of Dyer Lathrop and Jane Ann Shields Lathrop. Dyer Lathrop was a wholesale and retail merchant in Albany, New York, and one of the founders of the Albany Orphan Asylum. Her maternal grandfather, Daniel Shields, was a Revolutionary War soldier and later served as the Sergeant at Arms for the New York Assembly. Jane L. Stanford's siblings included Anna Maria Lathrop Hewes, wife of David Hewes, San Francisco businessman; Charles Lathrop, business manager for Jane Stanford and the University; and Daniel Shields Lathrop.
Description of the Collection
These papers pertain to the Lathrop family, in particular Dyer Lathrop and Daniel Shields. Dyer Lathrop's papers, 1820-1849, pertain largely to his business affairs and include letters, bills, notes, and receipts, including accounts with the Spring Street Mission House, 1828-1833. Daniel Shields' papers,1807-1835, largely concern his pension as a Revolutionary soldier and his appointment as Sergeant at Arms for the New York Assembly; other items include a ledger and an appraisal of his estate. Other papers of note in the collection include a list of donations to the Albany Orphan Asylum, 1833; insurance accounts of Charles Lathrop, 1908-1915; and a letter to Elizabeth Shields, Sept. 23, 1850, that mentions the wedding of Jane Lathrop and Leland Stanford.
Access Terms
Albany Orphan Asylum.; Lathrop family.; Lathrop, Charles G. (Charles Gardner), 1849-1914.; Lathrop, Dyer, 1787-1855.; Shields, Daniel.; Stanford, Jane Lathrop, 1828-1905.; Stanford, Leland, 1868-1884.; New York (State) --History --19th century.; Pensions, Military --United States --Revolution, 1775-1783.
Collection Contents
- Papers
  - Albany Orphan Asylum - miscellaneous documents, 1830-1833 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Fenn, James - extract of his will (2 different manuscript copies) (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Genealogy- notes (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Genealogy- notes and clippings (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Hewes, Anna Maria Lathrop
    - In Memoriam - Anne Lathrop Hewes, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Resolution of the death of Mrs. D. Hewes, passed by the Golden Gate Kindergarten Association (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Lathrop, Charles
    - Bank book, 1894-1895; Insurance accounts, 1908-1915 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Memorial Services program, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Lathrop, Daniel S. - In Memoriam, ca. 1883 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Lathrop, Delos - misc. estate papers, 1835 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Lathrop, Dyer
    - Appointment as fireman, 1826 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Bills, notes, receipts, etc., 1833-1849 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Legal documents, 1823-1835 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Letters to Jane Ann Lathrop, 1836 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Letters from Elijah Huntington, 1830 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Letters from Elijah Huntington, 1831 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Letters from Elijah Huntington, 1832 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Letters from Lathrop family members, 1824-1852 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Letters from others, 1820-1855 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Lathrop, Jane A. - Memorial, 1885 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Lathrop family, miscellaneous letters and documents
    - E.S. Barrows, Oswego, NY, to "the engraver, Albany, NY" re instructions for design for county medical association, 1829 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Letter to W. Lathrop with condolences on death of his father, 1855 Apr. 20 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Epitaph for unnamed person with bill on reverse, 1824 May 17 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Misc. accounts, 1818-1823 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Insurance Receipt: D. Lathrop Estate, 1880 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Biographical information on Ariel Lathrop (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Shields, Daniel
    - Appointment as Sergeant at Arms, New York Assembly
      - Ptd. D.S. Daniel Shields' application for Sgt. at Arms N.Y. House of Assembly (2 copies) and a handwritten current copy, 1824 Nov. (Box 1, Folder 21)
      - Ptd. letter Clarkson Crolius recommending Shields to Assembly, 1825 Nov. 12 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      - Ptd. D. Daniel Shields' application for Sgt. at Arms N.Y. House of Assembly, 1825 Nov. 12 (2 copies) (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Estate, Certificate and appraisal of personal effects, 1835 Oct. 17 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Ledger, 1823 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Letters received
      - A.L.S. David Forman to Shields, mentions package of letters received from Col. Willit - gives partial list, an extract of Lafayette letter and copy of Geo. Washington letter, 1828, Jan 30. (Box 1, Folder 24)
      - A.L.S. Ambrose Spencer to D.S. can't get cadet appointment for son, 1830 Mar. 20 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Military service and pension - documents and letters
      - Affidavit by Henry R. Teller, 1810 (Box 1, Folder 25)
      - Affidavit by Shields re his service, 1821 (Box 1, Folder 25)
      - A.L.S. John W. Taylor to S. Southwick Shield's pension, 1824 May 25 (Box 1, Folder 25)
      - A.L.S. DeWitt Clinton to Gen. Q. Smith introducing Shields and recommending him for position in the Custom House, 1824 Aug. 7 (Box 1, Folder 25)
      - A.L.S. Nathan Sanford to Shields re pension bill, 1826 Apr. 21 (Box 1, Folder 25)
      - Ptd. L.S. Richard Rush to D.S. re: claim request received, 1828 June 27 (Box 1, Folder 25)
      - Ptd. L.S. Richard Rush to D.S. re: claim granted, 1828 July 24 (Box 1, Folder 25)
      - Ptd. L.S. W.C. Clark to D.S. enclosing draft for $40, 1828 Oct. 23 (Box 1, Folder 25)
      - Ptd. L.S. ___ to D.S. enclosing draft for $40, 1833 Mar. 16 (Box 1, Folder 25)
      - Ptd. circular letter, F.B. Taney re: halfyearly payments of pensions, 1834 June 19 (Box 1, Folder 25)
      - Ptd. circ. letter, J.L. Edwards to D.S. re: pension payments, 1835 Aug. 5 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Military service pension - copies of documents prepared for Jane L. Stanford
      - A.L.S. G. Washington Ball to J.L.S. tracing service of Daniel Shields, 1892 May 28 and 1893 Jan. 23 (Box 1, Folder 26)
      - Statement from Bureau of Pensions, 1892 (Box 1, Folder 26)
      - Copies of documents re Daniel Shields (Box 1, Folder 26)
      - D.A.R. Application partially completed. (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Miscellaneous papers
      - An Act to incorporate St. Andrew's Society, 1807 Mar. 27 (Box 1, Folder 27)
      - Bond with Cornelius Miller, 1813 Dec. 4 (Box 1, Folder 27)
      - Bond as guardian of Alexander Shields, 1825 Sept. (Box 1, Folder 27)
      - Bond with Eli Berry & Dyer Lathrop, 1835 May 11 (Box 1, Folder 27)
      - Notes and receipts, 1814-1824 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Shields, Elizabeth - miscellaneous papers
    - A.L.S. Elizabeth Hoyt re family news and marriage of Jane Lathrop to Leland Stanford, 1850 Sept. 23 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - A.L.S. Mary Mott re news of family and friends, 1856 Apr. 6 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Ptd. letter Samuel H. Marks to Elizabeth Shields, pension, 1858 June 8 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Ptd. letter S.H. Marks to Elizabeth Shields failure of pension bill, 1858 July 6 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Death notice Elizabeth Shields, 1867 (Box 1, Folder 28)